Alex Wendland

PHONE: +44 7854033626 GitHub: https://github.com/AlexWendland E-MAIL: alex@wendland.org.uk

WEBSITE: https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/maths/people/staff/wendland/

PERSONAL STATEMENT

Analytical, efficient and ethical mathematician, python programmer and data scientist. Thirsty for new knowledge, experience and ideas, I push myself to learn whilst searching out places to apply myself for the largest positive impact. I am driven by problem solving, automation and the development of those around me.

EDUCATION

2015 – 2020 PhD in MATHEMATICS, University of Warwick, Coventry
"Generalisations of Groups and Cayley Graphs" under the supervision of Agelos Georgakopoulos
2011 – 2015 Masters in MATHEMATICS, University of Warwick, Coventry
1st Class Hons (91% average)

2004 - 2011 Secondary school, Beechen Cliff School, Bath

A Levels: Further Maths (A^*) , Maths (A^*) , Physics (A)

KEY SKILLS

Developer-level languages: Python and LATEX

Working-level languages: Java, Git, C, SQL, and JavaScript

Tools: Github actions, Google suit, Docker, Kubernetes, notion and Web3. Transferable: Data analysis, visualisation, and interpretation, maths, statistics,

leadership, communication, problem solving, collaboration, agile organisation,

research, relationship building, and teaching.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

2021-CURRENT

Data Scientist - CRYPTOCOMPARE, LONDON

Data scientist, python developer, and cross-team problem solver in a Cryptocurreny data scaleup.

Product development

- Researched and presented on-chain product ideas to C-suit executives, taking into account our competitors' offerings, customer need and product team availability.
- Investigated competitor indices to develop a proprietary market ready, client-adjustable and computationally feasible consolidated orderbook index.
- Produced documentation to support product handover for customers, developers and data specialists.

Automated data quality and monitoring

- Collaborating with multiple product teams and the support team to improve data quality and visibility with python coded data monitoring reviewing 100GB's of data daily.
- Developed a CI/CD pipeline using docker, github actions, Azure cloud storage and kubernetes to improve transparency, maintenance and coordination of monitoring microservices.
- Managed data analysts and support staff to take over maintenance and development of the data monitoring via training seminars, pair coding sessions and documentation.

Partner relationship building

- Sought and built relationships with established data analytics and visualisation providers to display the quality of our data, forging a long-term, mutually-beneficial partnership.
- Found new marketing opportunities with database providers for quick publicity pushes that synched up with the launch of a new product.
- Cooperating with potential partners to provide key metrics for their market evaluation by providing in-depth statistics on the company's current and future capabilities.

Client delivery

- Worked with clients to research, scope out, and formalise metrics that provide them the greatest insight.
- Programmed microsevervices that calculate metrics on TBs of data in cloud storage, delivered daily and historically.
- Coordinated analyst, product and delivery teams to ensure quality-assured data deliveries to multiple clients.

Team leadership and management

- Created and led a data science team with a cross-company jira board, weekly reporting to the c-suit executives, quarterly retrospectives to improve efficiency and a relationship with the Chief Operations Officer.
- Run month blockchain training for 20 people and coached analysts in python at a weekly workshop.
- Interviewed and hired a PhD student intern and data analyst.
- Wrote an analysts handbook in notion for team members and set up an introductory 3-week python training on github.
- Line managing two team members with one-to-ones, formal evaluations and seeking out continuing professional development.

2020-2021

Civil Service, Science and Engineering Fast Stream – CABINET OFFICE, LONDON The Fast Stream is a competitive leadership programme that develops individuals' communication, organisational and leadership skills.

Project management

- Project-managed high-profile technical reports with multiple stakeholders within the Advisory Council for the Misuse of Drugs: ACMD advice on consumer cannabidiol (CBD) products and Consideration of barriers to research: part 1.
- Managed internal stakeholders by developing road maps, regular updates, and resolving different requirements, and external stakeholders by organising call for evidence sessions, evidence gathering sessions, and public correspondence.
- Organised the analysis of the departmental staff survey to derive key targets and objects, increasing inclusivity and diversity.

2011-2020

Academia – University of Warwick

Algebraic graph theory PhD student driven by problem-solving, teaching and community building.

Research

- Built a portfolio of papers in leading journals such as Advances in Mathematics, Annals of Applied Probability and the Journal of Graph Theory.
- Established a strong academic record, earning the Ron Lockhart Student Prize in 2013 and undertaking 2 funded research projects during my undergraduate degree.
- Undertook a UKRI policy internship where I taught myself Natural Language Processing in python to match policy makers to academic experts using the Centre for Science and Policy's database.
- Attending multiple European Study Groups with Industry I worked with a group of mathematicians on an industrial problems such as adversarial image classification for the MOD's Defense, Science and Technology Laboratory, and scheduling problems for Heathrow airport.

Communication and teaching

- Teaching all levels and formats: lecturing masters level courses to helping underprivileged A-Level students one-on-one, winning the student voted Postgraduate teaching award in 2017
- Attended multiple conferences and spoken at many universities including: Cambridge, Iceland, Imperial College and Oxford.
- Earning funding in 2013 from JISC to develop a virtual learning platform in django (python).

Organisation and leadership

- Chairing the main student forum for change within the department for 3 years and member of multiple departmental committees and university societies, I actively organised networking events, ran extra academic sessions and rallied for change in the interest of the students. Earning the "giving to Warwick prize" in 2014.
- Representative on the diversity committee, earning the Bronze Athena Swan award in 2019 for the Maths department.
- Organising the weekly postgraduate seminar and board games night as well as additional social activities such as the infamous Christmas party I built the postgraduate community.

INTERESTS AND ACTIVITIES

I enjoy running, cycling, hiking, climbing, podcasts, board games and politics. I am actively involved in effective altruism and have given the Pledge.